A Guide to the Charles Eliot Norton Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8381
Charles Eliot Norton Collection 1851
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8381
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] [ 1966 Sep 12 ]
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Preface, "Lectures and Fragments of Lectures by James Russell Lowell" by Charles Eliot Norton, TMsS, 4 p.
    [Includes author's corrections and addition.] (Bound volume also contains essay "Humor, wit, and fun" and engraving and print of Charles Eliot Norton)
  - Essay, " Humor, wit, and fun " by James Russell Lowell, TMsS, 24 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections by Charles Eliot Norton. ]
- Letters
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Charles E. Guild, 1851 Aug 31; ALS, 5 p.
    [Regards Longfellow and other friends.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to unknown, 1859 Apr 22; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks correspondent for information pertaining to his Eliot ancestors; says a witch jury-man is of special interest; wishes to borrow the Eliot family printed genealogy.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to unknown, 1866 Apr 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refers to a letter by the correspondent which appeared in
    The North American Review
    mentions that [George] Bancroft fled the country on the mere report of the letter's appearance.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to unknown, 1877 Jul 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs correspondent that he was chosen to be a member of the Saturday Club. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Houghton, Mifflin & Co., 1883 May 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses thanks for a copy of advance sheets of a new edition of Jones Very's poems; praises the spiritual intensity and sincerity of the poems and is glad that they are published.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Editor of Century Magazine [ Richard Watson Gilder], 1884 Jan 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses the oldest known portrait of Dante; he states that the portrait in the Bargello in Florence was not by Giotto but by one of his pupils.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Carl Wilhelm Ernst, 1887 Apr 12; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for sending him an article about letters by Goethe that appeared in the
    Athenaeum
    . ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Edmund Clarence Stedman, 1887 Jul 27; ALS, 3 p.
    [Refers to John Norton and permits Stedman to make use of his own writings.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Bayard Wyman, 1887 Aug 9; ALS, 2 p.
    [Refuses a request to write a critical opinion on the work of Tolstoy.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to George Pellew, 1888 Mar 3; ALS, 4 p.
    [Replies after having received an article by him in defense of the works of Williams Dean Howells; interprets "realists" and "actualists" among writers, stating that "actualists" are seldom artists of the highest rank and gives examples of both.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Richard Watson Gilder, 1890 Mar 28; ALS, 3 p.
    [Refers to a letter by James Russell Lowell which, to his great satisfaction, is in the hands of Gilder for later publication; reports on Lowell's health.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Willis Hatfield Hazard, 1893 Feb 1; ALS, 2 p.
    [Informs him that he might find the passages from the
    Bible
    referred to in the
    Divine Comedy
    in an essay "
    Dante e la Bibbia
    " by Niccolo Tommaseo. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1894 Jan 11; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses publication of the James Russell Lowell papers in the
    Century
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Henry Paret, 1894 Mar 19; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends the requested autograph of his father, Andrews Norton. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to the Rev. J[ulius] H[ammond ?] Ward, 1894 Mar 19; ALS, 4 p.
    [Letter of recommendation regarding J. H. Jones, a student at Harvard, who would like to obtain a position as a reporter at the
    [Boston ?] Herald
    to report on the proceedings and papers of
    The Schools of Social Ethics
    mentions Crawford Howell Toy. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Messrs. Harper Brothers, 1894 Jul 28; ALS, 4 p.
    [Gives suggestions on how to improve the appearance of the book,
    Literary and Social Essays
    , by George William Curtis, which is about to be printed; points out number of misprints in the last volume of
    From the Easy Chair
    and makes corrections.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Gerard Roberts, 1895 Oct 9; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for sending a 30 year old notices from the
    Atlantic Monthly
    of the translation of
    Vita Nuova
    by Norton.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Howe, 1896 Jan 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Complies with request for titles of books on the art of painting as practiced by the Egyptians.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to William Gibbs Peckham, 1896 Jun 8; ALS, 3 p.
    [Recalls a visit to Bryn Mawr where he enjoyed a friendly reception by Peckham and his student daughter, who will be coming to Cambridge. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to William Gibbs Peckham, 1897 Mar 8; TLS, 1 p.
    [Includes autograph postscript acknowledging letter and cheque for the Memorial Library in memory of Mr. Child; voices his concern about future national politics; says he has noticed Peckham's name on the list of visiting committees to Harvard. ]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to William Gibbs Peckham, 1898 Apr 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Expresses his concern and anxiety about the nation.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Hinckley Gilbert [Thomas] Mitchell, 1899 Mar 17; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives the requested title of a book containing all of Dante's works:
    Tutte le Opere di Dante Alighieri
    by Dr. Edward Moore; mentions the cancellations of one of his readings.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to unknown, 1900 Oct 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives a short description of the life of Charles C. Burleigh, an abolitionist and lawyer; comments on Burleigh's friendship with fellow abolitionist James Russell Lowell; mentions
    William Lloyd Garrison, 1805-1879: The story of his life told by his children
  - Charles Eliot Norton to Franklin Benjamin Sanborn, 1901 Jun 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Mentions
    Ralph Waldo Emerson
    by Sanborn for the "Beacon Biographies of Eminent Americans" and
    The Correspondence of Thomas Carlyle and Ralph Waldo Emerson, 1834-1872
    , which he plans to reissue.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to William Gibbs Peckham, 1907 Mar 11; TLS, 1 p.
    [Includes autograph postscript thanking him for the third series of verse from the
    Harvard Advocate
    expresses hope that in this generation there may be one poet of creative originality, etc.]
  - Charles Eliot Norton to William Gibbs Peckham, 1907 Apr 13; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for sending his memorial pamphlet on R. R. Sinclair; points out the merits of Sinclair.]
- Prints
  - Printed photograph of Charles Eliot Norton, seated, n. d.; Photograph
    [In bound volume with TMs of "Humor and Wit."]
  - Printed etching by Hollyer of James Russell Lowell, head and shoulders, Etching